this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program
welcome listeners to another episode of
software engineering radio this is an
episode that we do through Skype and we
hope Skype will work for us on the other
end is Shane Clifford he works for
intentional software which kind of
defines the topic for this episode
intentional programming intentional
software welcome Shane hi Markus thanks
okay so why don't you introduce yourself
to our listeners so they know who you
are and then we can talk about what you
do I am the lead engineer for
intentional software's Belleview
development team and I've been with
intentional software for close to five
years now and we've been working on our
new technology for software development
mmm-hmm so what is that 10,000 feet
overview and then we can go into details
so intentional software is about doing
domain oriented or language oriented
development and the idea is that we we
capture the contributions from domain
experts and were you know experts in in
the in the field of the the target
problem for the software in a in a
structured syntax mm-hmm so so I mean it
sounds to me like domain-specific
languages yes it is domain-specific
languages but one of the things that
intentional brings is that it's it's all
natively structured in what we call an
intentional tree and then using this
this structured format for for all of
the the intentional languages allows us
to be very expressive in the ways that
we both edit and transform and generate
code from from that source okay so so
the general approach is basically as in
well from a very high-level perspective
you
uuuugh capture things with specifically
created languages and then you generate
code from that to make it executable I
mean that's kind of what everybody does
who does their sales and monitoring
development so I guess there are there
is this thing that your editor works
differently right so it's not like right
people type in characters right so it's
a it's a structured editing environment
you're you are always you know editing
the intentional tree and not editing a
textual syntax that is later parsed or
otherwise you know changed into an
abstract syntax tree of some kind we're
we're always manipulating a tree
directly in the editor and then what
typically you will be editing is a is a
what we call a projection of the
intentional tree and this allows us to
capture many different and very specific
notations that apply to the domains in
question
okay that we can you know better
represent in the editor the sort of
native notations for the experts
involved in that particular software
system for example a you know electrical
circuitry or mathematical notations so
these sorts of things so let's dive down
on this a little bit if you say
mathematic if you say mathematical
notation I mean I can write x equals x
plus 1 that's mathematical but that's
kind of boring I can express that with
ASCII so in contrast to that what kind
of notations can you express or can you
show or render or edit with this kind of
approach can you illustrate that a
little bit well we can do you know
summation symbols for summation
equations integrals you know we can we
can show division as a horizontal line
you know these these sorts of varied and
much more close to what people would
prefer to write by hand or look at when
they are they're reading a
a textbook or a paper that's written in
that in that domain mm-hmm so is it fair
to say that if we compare intentional to
other DSL stuff that what kind of
distinguishes your approach most is the
extreme freedom regarding notation yeah
that's certainly a large distinction I
think the other big distinction that we
have is the the underlying mechanism of
the intentional tree which allows us to
represent many different aspects or or
parameterizations of the information
while at the same time editing
projections or the reason we call the
the Edit the editing views that you see
projections is that they are really are
just slices of the end of that
particular intentional tree for the
purpose of editing in that particular
notation the the underlying tree may in
fact contain many other aspects of the
of the software system being described
that aren't represented in in the
particular projection that someone is
using to edit with with their favorite
notation so we may have you know a very
high-level projection of a tree that
that has you know just something very
specific to a particular domain experts
area of interest well at the same time
that tree could contain your very
low-level programming information in in
other parts of the tree and we can get
into a little more detail about how that
works so the the intentional tree is
different from let's say an abstract
syntax tree in that the abstract syntax
tree captures the abstract syntax of one
language whereas the intentional tree
captures let's say everything and then
different view views on that different
projections can be used to edit a
certain aspect of this everything
correct the we we create schemas in
intentional software that apply to the
intentional tree but they do not define
the structure of the intentional tree
all intentional trees have the same
underlying structure at the lowest level
and what our what our schemas provide is
a a set of rules if you will for
participating in that domains
capabilities its projections its code
generators its its other transformations
mm-hmm so again if I contrast that with
classical language engineering
approaches if you would let's say
describe if you would have well
classically speaking one language to
describe components and interfaces and
then another language to describe the
implementation of the components then
classically in classical approaches
these would be two different languages
and you would refer let's say from an
implementation block to a component to
define what the implementation of that
component is in intentional you can
basically put all of that into one model
into one intentional tree you don't have
to have separate languages you only have
different projections to cater for what
different stakeholders developer roles
need yes that that's certainly true
frequently we do have separate languages
okay as well it's just that we're not a
single intentional tree is not
constrained to only participate in one
language right right so the schema
doesn't define the storage structure or
anything is really just a view or a way
of interacting with this data precisely
and and the fact that it doesn't define
the storage structure is is very
important because it allows us a lot of
flexibility in being able to extend and
and grow languages or add new aspects of
a system into a tree over time without
disturbing or or otherwise impacting the
already existing functionality that's
represented or the information that has
already been captured yeah so so what's
the what is the structure of the
intentional tree what's the abstraction
of describing the tree so the the
intentional tree is made up of something
we just call a node and each node you
know nodes form the intentional tree
in a in a primarily hierarchical
relationship so we have a node and then
each node has fields okay and the the
real key here is that there there's no
constraints on the number of fields that
a given node can have and all fields are
strongly identified and all nodes are
strongly identified and so it within and
then within each field of a node can be
one or more additional nodes so that
forms the the basic hierarchy of the
intentional tree now the other key to
the intentional tree is that the way
that nodes and fields are identified is
by reference to other intentional nodes
I guess you need to land that so we we
have a node in a program tree for
example representing an addition
equation let's say 1 plus 2 so the the
top node in that tree is a plus right
and then it has let's say a field for
its its left argument and a field for
its right argument and the left argument
field contains a node representing 1 and
the and the right argument contains a
node representing two ok now clearly I'm
going to want to have many different
pluses in a given intentional tree right
so there is another intentional tree
that contains the definition of plus
that describes what plus is and the the
plus node in our in our 1 plus 2 gets
its its identity it's it's what it is
from that by referring to that other
node that represents the definition of
plus ok so we see interns rep which
which intern
references something a node in the
system we call deaf which is how we
describe or define nodes in the trees so
this this gets its identity by or is
described by sounds to me a little bit
like the classical instance of thing
right that the plus here is an instance
of the concept or the metaclass or the
whatever plus yes it is an instance of
relationship and in fact we we call the
relationship and is a relationship okay
okay and and then fields are similarly
identified by by reference to other
nodes okay good so so I guess I guess
people can imagine that what I hope so
and and there are certainly some videos
online that illustrate that and we link
to those that if you have complete
freedom regarding the notation that you
can do quite some impressive things and
we'll discuss examples later but let's
first address the question of how you
actually create languages I mean if I'm
a developer who goes to a customer who
works in the XYZ domain and I want to
help them build a language for that XYZ
domain how would I go about that I mean
you mentioned the term schema I mean how
do I do that
okay so defining a schema really just
starts with with identities and we need
to give names to things and in any given
problem space the people that are
already involved in that in in in
solving problems in that space usually
will have a fairly rich and deep
language that they can speak about their
problem space in and so we just need to
capture those those words those
identities that they are familiar with
and comfortable with already and so the
the real key is just first come up with
those those important concepts from our
domain and represent those using as I
mentioned earlier we we have a
domaine already defined in the system
for defining domains and so it has its
own you know set of words and identities
that we we as domain domain developers
have to become familiar with and
comfortable with and and so it starts
with a something we call a domain def
and a domain def allows us to just to
describe you know in a simplified form
it's a collection of of Deaf's and def
is another identity in this in this
domain for defining domains so so Deaf's
are kind of the meta classes and that
domain Deficit kind of package if you
will right right sure the domain def
Fiat yes is the collection of meta
objects yeah the and so for each
important concept that we identify in a
domain we can create a def to represent
that concept and once we're comfortable
that we have a pretty good idea of what
all of the concepts are we can start
moving into the relationships between
those concepts you know what you know
what is kind of the the primary concept
here or are there are there several
primary concepts and we can create
relationships between them using field
deaths and so we can describe the the
fields the parameterization of each of
each concept in the domain of each def
using field deaths at wherein we can say
you know for this given field of this
def these are the other kinds of deaths
that can be put in this field
some things may contain numbers other
things may contain a list of different
kinds of deaths you know and there's a
lot of freedom there to you know
describe you know very restrictive or
very free domains because you know
different domains have different needs
as far as the one of the concepts we
like to use a lot in essential software
is degrees of freedom yeah yeah and the
the there's there's an appropriate
degree as a degree of freedom for each
problem that you will encounter in a
software system
and the goal of intentional software is
to provide the exact right degree of
freedom for solving that problem so that
the the person who is solving the
problem the person who eventually is
writing domain code or describing a
system using this language that we
create has all of the freedom they need
but no more than that well and and and
on the other hand they shouldn't have
well you have to be able to write
generators by consuming the models or
domain code they write so each of the
degrees of freedom that is in the system
must be meaningful and you need to know
how to treat it and what to do with it
so that's maybe another constraint here
absolutely
you know one of the I think one of the
advantages of the intentional tree is
that it provides us such a rich yet
common framework for building these
transformations that it's actually in my
experience I've I found it it's pretty
difficult actually to you know design a
language or to come up with an oat a
Schnoor languages that that somehow make
it difficult or impossible to generate
code that I think it's um typically what
what you find is that given the the the
freedom to to really manipulate these
trees and and alter them and transform
them into other trees that that you
usually don't run into any you know
issues with the note the syntax that you
come up with not technically but I mean
you just need to know the semantics of
what all the stuff that people have
freedom to write actually means so you
can fully translate it to something else
that's been right
okay so we have deaths we have fields
that's that's that's kind of a schema
definition that's what you would do well
not in not exactly the same way but kind
of the same way if you did a UML
metamodel or something what what else do
we have I mean at this point we just
have a schema we can't edit things yet
right we have some
built-in projections in the system that
allow us to project any intentional tree
based on a schema that's been designed
make a generic so when you thing right
so once you once you have your schema
defined you can immediately begin
creating documents based on that schema
using a very generic tree like project
set of projections but yes then you
can't begin to define your own
projections that more closely match the
the notations of the domain in question
and there is a language we have for
describing projections called
we call it the a language for abstract
syntax notation language abstract
language a and the a language is a set
of of definitions deaths that that our
system understands how to transform
further into the various notations that
you can put on the screen such as tables
and charts and and and graphs or or
stuff that looks like you know
programming syntax paragraphs and
chapters of text the mathematical
equations that we mentioned earlier
mm-hmm so entries yeah so projection is
basically a a model to model
transformation from your own from your
own domain to an existing domain that
can be rendered exactly we have a a
language and you transform you write
transformations and they we have a
fairly templated capability for doing
the transformations where you know
similar to XSLT you know that's sort of
a system wherein you can transform
through these sets of rules one trend
one tree one intentional tree into
another and in the case of a projection
it's
to a tree in the in this a language
which yes is then renderable to the
screen or to you know for printing or or
even into text files and the you know in
the middle case of of generating source
code yeah and and and the the a language
as you said is on the level of tables
cell assignment kind of thing right is
that how is that then actually rendered
I mean it's that transfer whether or
what's the abstraction level at which
you actually draw the lines at pixels so
we have internal to the system there
there is a series of transformations
that that takes the the a language that
is produced by by domain to a
transformations the projection
transformations and eventually draws
that on the screen and yes we have a
series of three different languages that
we move through and depending on you
know the the eventual goal for the
output some of the the the languages we
move to it toward the end can vary but
for the most part the a language goes to
something we call the C language which
is a concrete language like a like a
layout language something similar to you
know lay tech I suppose yeah that'd be a
good analogy for the for the C language
and then from that language we now have
a very nicely structured you know we
know how tall the lines of text are we
know the the layout of graph nodes and
their connections from there we
transform into something we call the G
language which is our graphical language
and then that language in turn is
something that's you know down to the
pixel and and color and the order and
all of the you know the necessary
information that we can actually call
the
rendering API of the of the os/2 to
actually draw the the images on the
screen is probably quite do it is or
once probably quite a challenge to make
that stuff perform well because I mean
if you change something on the
projection level you know a 1 + 3 you
change it to 1 + 2 you have to go
through all these levels and then
actually render the pixels differently
yes it certainly is and you know we've
we've really that's a big part of of
where our time has been spent on
intentional technology is is really
making the the underlying
transformations perform and you know a
big key there is is is partial
transformation yeah you know we we have
the ability to recognize you know which
parts of the tree are actually affected
by changes in in earlier trees and the
transformation pipeline is what we call
it we call it a pipe you know if
transformations where each stage of the
the pipe is the transformation from one
tree to another and so by detecting the
the you know smallest possible sections
of each tree that can be sort of altered
by a given edit we can really improve
the the efficiency and speed of doing
these projections okay now we have
schema we have editor definition by
projection I guess there are two more
things missing at least there is
validation what what's typically called
probably constraints or something I
guess you have something for that - sure
we have a validation API that we can you
you can associate validations with the
definitions and fields and your schema
that can have any you know any number of
various sorts of constraints that you
can apply in terms of you know the kinds
of definitions that can actually be
referenced in a given field when when
when you start to have languages where
the the domain actually describes things
that will be then referred to from other
places in the domain I mean the obvious
example in programming is you define a
procedure or a method on a class and
then you're going to refer to that from
other places yeah and so you you start
to have scoping rules about you know am
I actually allowed to refer to this
procedure from this place and the in the
tree so all of that can be handled via
the the validation API and then we also
do have a what we call a type calculus
API as well that allows you to actually
assign a type system to the instances of
of definitions in your language and and
it you know provide validation of a for
an actual you know static type system as
well yeah things like you can only add
numbers and not a number in the string
things like that absolutely yeah okay I
guess the last step that's kind of
necessary for systems like that is is
what's probably called cogeneration how
does that work
so cogeneration in intentional software
right now has a couple of different
forms that it can take of there's the
primary form that we we choose to use is
just very similar to what we do with
projections and in fact the typical last
stage of most of our cogeneration code
generators is in fact a projection okay
so we we start out by just doing a
transformation much like the one we
described earlier from the domain of the
the problem space to some other domain
and typically that other domain is a
programing domain a programming language
domains such as c-sharp or Java or Ruby
okay and so we have defined schemas for
those other languages in our system and
then we can we can target
transformations
of the domain code to those other
languages in much the same way that we
did to do the projections from the
domain
today language mm-hm and and so that
that provides a a sort of first stage of
create a Java tree or a Ruby tree from
my domain and now we can just transform
that Ruby or Java tree using a
projection to a notation that is valid
code for that domain so we can we can we
can through the series of
transformations choose choose constructs
in the a language that generate you know
valid Java text or valid Ruby text and
and then we have a replacement stage at
the end of the pipe that rather than
going to our G language which is in
renderable to the os's rendering engine
we can actually instead just take our C
language and go directly to a text file
okay and then from there we can hand
that text file or you know a collection
of text files if you will in end and
generate you know hand hand that
generated output over to the compiler or
interpreter of the target language yeah
where execution yeah so in some sense
the cogeneration is projections that
aren't executed in real time but only on
demand basically exactly and we you know
and then the other approach that you
could take you know for certain specific
situations is is to just write code that
simply you know walks the intentional
tree of your domain and and it makes
calls to your own you know API or or
builds you know any other source or tree
from that you know from the intentional
tree and I guess one of the languages
you have in your system is a text
language which contains of things like
character word
and in worst case you can always kind of
transform to that than just serialize it
oh absolutely yeah absolutely you could
just transform directly into the yeah we
have a text editing domain the anti
cheese yeah so and then you're of course
on the hook for a lot of the formatting
which you know if you if you choose you
know typically I think even if it's a
even if your target is is a language
that we don't already support I think
you'll get more value from representing
it as a domain first and projecting that
domain yeah rather than then trying to
just go directly from domain code to
text yeah so there are situations where
it can where it can work if you have
just you know the the domain code is
simply trying to generate you know
configuration files yeah exactly so you
know for a that will will process those
files yeah I'm thinking of OSGi manifest
right now so I guess yeah whatever we
talked about the fact before that you
for that for one intentional tree you
can have different views different
projections does this also include the
possibility to have for the same concept
different projections or maybe even
project the same thing differently in
different contexts is that also possible
the same thing differently in different
contexts yes absolutely we well and we
certainly you know you can you can
define many different projections for
the same domain I thought maybe that's
the the question you're getting at or
that's that's the a and you can also
define properties that can be applied to
the view in order to parameterize the
projections to produce different results
you know you can you know there are many
built into the system for example
changing the the background color or
foreground color of the of the
projection or changing the font size or
you know the actual font think things
like that but then you could also
introduce your own properties that
actually prep parameterize
your your domain projection that you
know might say okay if the user chooses
to turn on this property on this on this
node then I'm going to project it as a
table rather than a graph okay or you
know something it's something of that
nature and of course things are always
editable because it's not a
visualization it's actually a live
projection absolutely re-emphasize yes
yes okay and and in fact even you know
one of the one of the nice things with
using the transformations and
projections for the code generators is
that we can actually produce editable
views in the target programming
languages you know I can I can have a
domain code that targets Ruby and then
actually show that in the editor in its
Ruby form and then perhaps edit
additional fields of that of that domain
tree that may not be available in the
domain code projection but are available
in the Ruby projection so to add add
additional code annotations add
additional code into the tree in that
Ruby projection because it is all
editable that's an interesting way to
look at it because assuming the Ruby
thing is really just a projection of the
same intentional tree without any
transformation that I can easily imagine
how that would work but if if you create
the intention the Ruby representation by
actually really a transformation and
then you change something in the in the
result of the transformation by adding
additional code then if you regenerate
reach transform is that code not
overwritten I mean how do you invalidate
the results of transformations I guess
that's what I'm getting it well the
there can certainly be there will
certainly be parts of any transformation
that that may not be editable because
they are they spring into existence in
the transformation yeah yeah right so so
if there there's very likely to be some
constructs in the in the
Rubi projection if you will of some
domain that is not editable yeah okay
there were in that in that view however
we can make the projection you know
basically in the way that we do our
projections or our transformations we
can provide the the adequate mapping and
editing rules during the transformation
such that we can actually make those
edits and have them have them go into
the that underlying intentional tree
which remember we said can contain any
fields you know the the schema of our
language is never controlling the actual
underlying storage structure yeah but
it's actually just describing a
particular layout for a tree to
participate in that domains capabilities
so some nodes in the tree might come
from the schema defined for let's say
some insurance domain and then other
nodes come from a ruby domain which you
use to add additional code manually
written code to the stuff transformed
out of the insurance stuff right okay
exactly and then and then your insurance
projection can safely ignore the Ruby
code that it does not understand and not
present that to the insurance expert
yeah well the the code remains in the
the overall domain structure of the the
underlying tree for the programmers
purpose
I guess if your if your if your
insurance protection is guided by the
schema defined for the insurance domain
then it kind of doesn't even see the
other stuff it is it is in some fields
but it doesn't it's nowhere of it
alright and we actually we we have the
ability with our own underlying
projections to sort of enhance if you
will the the projections that people
write to actually show the underlying
stuff in the same view right in in a
sort of default way that I was in the
default way that I was describing
earlier so we can you know you could be
looking at the insurance specific
notation and say boy I'd really like to
see the
the Ruby code that's underlying this
here and sort of turn that on and we
will inject that that transformation
into the the insurance projection so
switch gears a little bit what is what
is which technology did you use to
actually implement the intentional
system as it is a bootstrap tour is what
is it based on so the there's an
underlying kernel of the intentional
system that was developed in in.net
you with using c-sharp mm-hmm so that
that provides this sort of very basic
underlying core and then some of the
lower-level transformations the some of
the the later stage transformations that
I was describing the the C language in G
language transformations that produce
the structure and and call the rendering
api's are are in fact implemented in in
c-sharp but much of the system is
actually bootstrapped in terms of you
know all of the the definitions that we
rely on for those languages are in fact
implemented and edited you know using
our intentional domain editor the
intentional domain workbench so we do we
do in fact have a significant portion of
the system at this point
bootstrapped into into our own
technology where we can you know define
new into the intentional domains and and
enhance the the capabilities of our
editor using its own technology
ok so let's switch gears again and take
a look at the existing well prototype
slash customers slash applications can
you give us an overview of which kinds
of systems you've built or are willing
to talk about or are showcased or
something sure we've we've done it's
pretty common knowledge I think we've
done several demos and and presentations
that have included it a system in the
pension administration space with
Capgemini you know
in the Netherlands yeah
and we've also you know had several
different people you know using the the
system for you know evaluation purposes
looking at ways that they could include
it in projects that they might have
upcoming or or you know in in other ways
that they might be able to take
advantage of the technology and we've
got another system that is getting you
know a project getting underway in in
Europe that is an information modeling
system in a medical domain and and I am
currently working on a domain for a
customer here in the in the United
States that say based on a forms and and
interviews for complying with some some
regulations okay the and so the the
domain expert in the in the case of that
particular example is is someone who's
well versed in the in the legal and you
know aspects of complying with the laws
and regulations and and can sort of
provide this this expert flow through an
interview that helps someone who is in
no way an expert you know the end user
of this application is intended to be
just a random person in a company who
you know they need to you know they've
been tasked with the job of helping
their company yeah you know comply with
these regulations and and they could
greatly benefit from having you know
some expert knowledge provided to them
that helps them sort of walk through a
series of questions that lets them drill
down to exactly the information they
need to provide and what form they need
to provide it in and and so it's a
pretty exciting domain where we can
really you know describe a language of
you know this these sort of series of
questions and
and in pieces of information that need
to be captured in a way that you know
the the domain experts who are you know
these legal experts can actually just
sort of write you know the this flow of
questions almost as if they were just
editing a word you know a document in or
word processing and then we can you know
generate a full-fledged web application
from this information to deploy out to
the end customers going back to the
pension domain can you maybe illustrate
a little bit the different notations
used in that system and and and and and
and why well and kind of how that it
exploits the the capabilities of the
intentional tooling so the the pension
domain involves you know defining a lot
of concepts the reguar around pensions
the rules of administering pensions and
and of defining you know when when
people's pensions take effect and you
know what their what their actual
benefits are over time and all
incorporating all of the laws and rules
and regulations of in this case it was
the the you know is the Dutch government
yeah
and so there's there there are notations
that are sort of very basic you know
decision tree type notations you know
where we have you know is effectively
simplified if-else ladders I mean in
some sense it's it's very it's very
similar to real programming and but the
the the form of the language again that
the degree of freedom is restricted in a
way that makes sense for the pension you
know expert and then there there are a
lot of tables in that domain it has a
very strong temporal aspect to it where
the rules can change over time and you
know the the and and so there's you know
tables that sort of
provide they provide a projection that
shows you know well for this time range
here was the rule for this time range
here were the rules here were the the
components involved so there are a lot
of tables and then and also tables were
used for presenting there's a in that
particular demand there was a strong
testing aspect of they really wanted to
be able to have integrated testing of
the domain code and the information that
the domain experts are providing which
is something that our system can do
really well because the you know the the
evaluation and of test data against the
rules can just be another you know sort
of projection and transformation and so
we had tables wherein they could define
the test inputs for you know
representing say a particular pensioner
and then the the results of the applying
the various rules to the that test input
would show up next to the rule in a
tabular form and and then we also had
because it does have that that sort of
you know if else--if structure to it to
the code but there was actually a
debugging projection that broke out the
the if-else projection into into a more
graphical tree like notation and
provided the the you know so that the
individual components of the calculation
and the decision tree were actually
shown each in their own graph node right
and with the result of evaluating that
particular statement with you know a
particular test data input yeah so you
could kind of that follow through the
the calculation as it progresses right
you know it's sort of like you know it's
just as if they had sat and used a desk
calculator to sort of do the
calculations and make the decisions and
they can just see the result of each
step of the process so they can you know
track down the error without having to
you know without the sort of you know
the programmers they're accustomed to
which is the you know the line stepping
yeah debugger yeah that we're also you
know in love with of course this works
especially well if you have fly you're
more or less functional language is
right I mean in some sense that's the
only way to debug functional expressions
absolutely yeah I seem to remember from
the presentations that there is also
some mathematical notations in that
system yes there are there are
mathematical notations there's a part of
the input actually comes from from
actuarial specialists yeah
actuaries that define the the underlying
rules that that extend into the rest of
the system and and they actually have a
it's it's not so much mathematical it's
actually a very specific notation it's
really interesting that actuaries
actually have a very specific notation
that includes its own set of symbols and
and identifiers yeah that we were able
to capture and I you know again it's
something that people will probably need
to see in a in a video or yeah um
capture to get a full flavor for it but
there's you know a lot of really you
know little intricate you know bars and
lines over letters that and superscripts
and subscripts that have very
significant meaning to people who
understand it yeah yeah and again that's
that's sort of the beauty of the whole
thing is that we you know as programmers
sometimes get you know almost forced
into you know becoming actuaries in
order to develop assume the that
supports actuaries and I think in you
know and this proof one of the things
that intentional software does very well
as it allows the the programmers to sort
of stay focused on the programming and
the support of you know the domain
experts and the code generation and and
not you know have to you know sort of
really come to fully understand maybe
the notation I mean clearly you need to
have a full understanding like you said
of the schema and do their generation
but you don't have to sort of keep in
your mind you know you can you can
provide this very rich editor that has
the
bars and lines and superscripts and
subscripts yeah without having to sort
of keep in your head what those
particular things mean you know they
they have they have very deep meaning
for the people who understand them and
so it's really nice to be able to give
it a tool like that to someone that has
you know this this deep meaning for them
yeah and then it is at the same time you
know providing you with this this great
you know underlying tree that you can be
very comfortable with transforming and
generating you know other output from of
course at some point somebody has to
understand the domain to be able to
define a schema and stuff but I guess
you do that once and and then you can
delegate all the detail work of actually
putting in the data that's what the
domain experts don't do sure I mean it's
you know you you have to understand it
from the point of building a language
around it and and there's no you know
it's no joke that there's you know
there's certainly a skill there that has
to be mastered in terms of taking this
yeah you know and I wouldn't say that
you do it once I think it is just it is
it can be a very iterative oh yeah yeah
yeah sure but but yeah I think I think
the the nice thing about it is that it
is much more collaborative than in many
other situations where you can actually
sit down with the domain expert and you
can define the language you know right
there with them and begin to sort of see
it take shape and take form and and get
their immediate feedback and work
through the the different situations and
you know issues that will come up yeah
and and it can be you know it becomes a
very fluid process really and I think
you know over time the the the nice
thing about it you know is that you know
you don't one of the things that I
really like about the intentional system
versus you know some others that that
there might be out there is that you
don't have to have any concern for the
language or or what your end user wants
to to represent you you don't have to
worry about coming up with something
that's personal right yeah sure yes
right and that is such a
is is it it provides such a nice freedom
yeah if you not have to you know always
be concerned with well you know we're
already using that kind of symbol here
so now we have this conflict and you
know there's there's sort of a you know
this great degree of freedom to you know
that really matters in that particular
case which is really being able to
capture exactly what your domain expert
is telling you and not having to make
unwanted compromises yeah so so if you
have this rich notation which is not
parsed so it's not ASCII text how do
people actually edit things in these
projections I mean is everything click
Mouse wise or how does that work uh well
we have a bill you know various keyboard
navigation mechanisms for navigating the
trees and and so you can you know use
the keyboard there is a lot of clicking
and it depends on the domain in the
situation and the the comfort level of
the you know the user in terms of how
they you know tend to use software and
how they tend to interact with
applications and of course software
developers tend to be the most demanding
domain experts in terms of the kind of
freedom and flexibility they expect from
you know editing their documents mm-hm
and you know in in the other in many
cases with with the more you know
domain-specific projections and
notations for you know end-user domains
like the the pension domain or this you
know interview domain we can actually
just provide the necessary click points
on the screen you know click here to add
you know this kind of question or yeah
click here to add some new test data and
you know dropdowns and in you know radio
buttons and things things like that that
allow people to choose their their their
inputs or the the structure of the
language that they they're they're
trying to produce right
so but we do have and in fact the the
next version of our of our system that
we're currently working on is is going
to actually include a much more robust
keyboard navigation system that allows
um much more much more geometric style
of keyboard navigation than we've had in
the past in the past we've we've had a
our keyboard navigation has more closely
followed the structure of the projection
projected tree okay and not not
necessarily the domain tree but the
actual the the structure of the the a
tree that you've produced now you're
projecting it and this worked and it
works quite well for a lot of domains
but there are also situations where it
just becomes sort of cumbersome and puts
an unnecessary the wrong burden of
understanding on the user in terms of
knowing right knowing sort of the
underlying structure yeah of what they
are looking at in order to get to the
place they want to be using the keyboard
whereas in our the the new navigation
system that we're we're about to deploy
actually provides you know a nice
on-screen cursor and you can you know up
means up and less less cool right me
right then and you can navigate around
in that in that way and you know it's
it's just using all of the information
we have from all of the trees through
the pipe to to sort of get you to the
right place based on what's underneath
the the cursor when you move there and
there's you know it it's so far seems to
be you know providing a much more fluid
more text like editing experience in the
domain tree so we're pretty excited
about it and and we feel like it's a
it's they're gonna be a really great
usability enhancement moving forward
that you know may have you know a
it's it'll it'll allow us to get into
even more complex domains than we and
then we've already been able to get into
because of the you know the the kinds of
tree structures that might be ripped and
and it might convince certain skeptical
programmer types who don't want to use
the mouse all the time absolutely
absolutely this this this next version
is much more friendly to the you know I
want to keep two hands on the keyboard
cool style of work very nice I'm looking
forward to that and maybe I should have
said in the beginning that then I was
once working for intentional as a
consultant and that I actually are
currently playing with the tools so I do
have some some bias or whatever you want
to call it and so I'm looking forward to
getting my hands on literally my hands
and on my mouse on on to version right
yeah well I think yeah people who have
used the system in the past I think will
will really appreciate it I think for
someone I like like myself I've I've
actually become so accustomed to the to
the current use use model it does work
with the model we have today works it's
just very different from from what you
know people are used to another software
but I've you know I've been working with
it for several years now so I'm I'm
actually in a position where I'm going
to be sort of unlearning you know the
the less desirable approach and you know
we'll probably actually stumble a little
bit with the new one but the I think
thing out but all of the feedback that
that we're getting from you know early
users and you know some of the other
people on our teams that are they're
using the new new stuff is that it
really really works nice and it really
you know sorts sort of it gets you to
the point where you can really start to
forget about the fact that you're that
there's some underlying structure to
what you're editing very very good okay
so let's let's let's close this
discussion off by going back to the very
beginning and maybe very briefly
covering the history of intentional
programming and intentional software and
then look at the current state of the
system so
so where does this thing come from how
long have you been doing it stuff so
intentional software is the company that
was you know we founded by Charles
Simoni in 2002 and prior to that it was
actually a research project at Microsoft
Research okay and you know Charles had
had led that that effort therefore for
several years I actually can't recall
exactly how long off the top of my head
right now but they you know and they
they made some you know they made some
nice improvements there they came up
with some good ideas they got a certain
distance with the system and then
Charles decided to move on to do to try
to move it forward
as a separate company so they started
with intentional software in in 2002 and
you know the the system has been through
several generations now internal
internally to the company as we've we've
worked through you know various
technical issues and and get it you know
trying to get the the technology you
know as you'd mentioned before the you
know making the the series of
transformations performing him such that
it's actually you know capable of being
a sort of you know real-time editing
environment has has been a key challenge
and we've gone through several
iterations in both you know trying to
trying to improve the performance and
also just I think one of the the key
things that happened along the way is we
we really improved the the flexibility
of the series of transformations to
really involve any number of of you know
domain to domain transformations and you
know any number of of languages or
schemas being involved in any given tree
and in order to to project it to the
screen or to a file and I think that is
really you know that has really been the
key in making this you know sort of a
rather than just being some kind of a
you know interesting research
to making something that's you know
viable for developing you know
production software so it is it is
released as version whatever one point
something or is it we're currently on
one point five mm okay and the the new
version upcoming that I was talking
about will be 1.6 okay and can people
get it or what's the process there
people can't get it there's a you can go
to our website and communicate with
Magnus Chris person and you know that
there's a process in place for getting
you know signed up to get an evaluation
license going and and or to you know
talk with us about you know working on
yeah projects together yeah talk about
that there is no not there's no download
for everybody to there is no download
right now we can you know there's not a
there's not a you know go here to just
download it and try it out yeah but okay
you know it is it is available upon
request
good okay well as I said before I'm
certainly very biased I think this this
kind of approach is is a very very very
interesting approach to doing things
we've had a short episode on chat brains
MPs before and then your stuff is is
certainly similar in from the conceptual
perspective and in my view a little bit
more flexible and more extreme in the
positive I think you know were we're
we're targeting a you know they're
slightly different yeah you know target
audiences and right I think you know the
the jetbrains
tool is is really and I think it's you
know it's it's a very good thing that
they're they're really you know trying
to get the benefit of domain-specific
languages into the hands of programmers
yes yes it's it's kind of developer tool
and it's in and that you know that
definitely has a lot of value I think
that the this pattern of you know
getting the the language that you are
developing your software in closer to
the domain is just a very powerful tool
and it's something that everyone should
should consider yes and you know we're
just you know we're sort of taking this
additional step of saying well if we
have the right technology then we can
you know put these these notations into
the hands of the domain experts and and
cut out that sort of next step of
inefficiency and and confusion and you
know source of source of error which is
that sort of the the inefficient
communication between the people driving
the requirements and and the the people
building the software if we can get the
people driving the requirements more
involved directly in in building the
software then the likelihood of a
positive outcome becomes much greater
yes I was about to ask you for for for a
bunch of closing words but I think what
you just said is actually a very nice
summary of what you're attempting of
what you're doing so I mean you can
still add another bunch of closing words
but if you don't want to then I guess
those qualified well I think that seems
like a pretty good summary to me too so
I guess we'll just leave it at that okay
then I thank you very much for being on
the show and well thank you for the
opportunity work is sure and looking at
looking forward to the to the to the
left means left navigation all right
thanks
bye bye
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio software engineer
radio is an educational program brought
to you by hillside Europe if you want
more information about the podcast and
all the other episodes visit our website
at se - radio dotnet if you want to
support us you can donate to the SU
radio team by our website or you can
advertise for su radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and the slash dot button to
contact the team please send email to
team at se - radio net or if it is
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under the
creative comments 2.5 license please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the pot size Music
Network for the music used in this show
the song is called Vegas Achtung